Good morning,
my name is Dan Margulis. I am a student at ישיבת חובבי
תורה Yeshivat Chovevei Torah and I am filling in for Rabbi Linzer
while he is on vacation. Today we are on נדרים Nedarim דף
מו, Daf Mem Vav, the beginning of פרק השותפין, Perek HaShutfin, and
we are going to go back over the משנה Mishnah that we
touched on yesterday and then go into the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. The
משנה Mishnah said: השותפין שנדרו הנאה זה מזה, Hashutfin shenadu hana’ah zeh
mizeh, if we have two business partners who have each of them
taken a שבועה shvuah one against the other, אסורים להיכנס לחצר, asurim
lehikanes lachatzer, so they are both prohibited from entering into the חצר
chatzer that they jointly own. So this is a case of people
who are neighbors, they each own some kind of rights to a
communal חצר chatzer between their two buildings perhaps, or it’s the hallway
of an apartment building, something like that, and because they each cannot
get הנאה hana’ah one from the other, the fact that each of
them have partial ownership means that neither of them can get benefit
from this חצר. chatzer. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר זה נכנס לתוך
שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer zeh nichnas
letoch shelo vezeh nichnas letoch shelo, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says
each one can enter into part of the חצר, chatzer, either the
part that is designated to his own use because even in the
communal space each of them have designated areas, or perhaps even if
we take the way the גמרא Gemara is going to explain it
later, in anywhere they go. Exactly, that if רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov is saying יש ברירה... yesh breira...
He’s reviewing the משנה. Mishnah.
So if רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov is saying...
we’re in the משנה Mishnah on מ"ה עמוד ב Mem Hei Amud
Bet and we’re going to then continue on מו. Mem Vav.
Okay, so if רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov is
saying יש ברירה, yesh breira, the concept that there is retroactive clarification
of the conditions of an agreement such that the fact that once
they’ve taken this נדר neder and once they have this partnership, it
can become clear later which part of the courtyard belongs to whom,
so then it would be possible to say that each of them
can go throughout the entire courtyard perhaps, or at least throughout most
of the courtyard even if they’re not designated areas because whatever you’re
using at that time you can say it was meant to be
mine.
Okay, so זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו, zeh nichnas
letoch shelo vezeh nichnas letoch shelo, ושניהם אסורים להעמיד ריחיים ותנור ולגדל
תרנגולים. ushneihem asurim leha’amid reichaim vetannur ulegadel tarnigolim. Things that in a
certain sense occupy a stationary space permanently in the חצר chatzer or
use the whole חצר, chatzer, whether they’re because they are a ריחיים
reichaim or a תנור, tannur, which are stationary and very heavy and
permanently occupy the space, or ולגדל תרנגולים ulegadel tarnigolim to raise chickens,
which seems like the chickens spread out and take up the entire
courtyard, then both of them would be prohibited because that would be
occupying in some sense either permanent occupation of part of the space
or even temporary but taking over the entire space. היה אחד מהם
מודר הנאה מחברו, Haya echad mehem mudar hana’ah mechaveiro, what if only
one of them takes a נדר neder against the other? לא יכנס
לחצר. Lo yikanes lachatzer. So
who does it mean? He cannot go into the חצר chatzer and
who was מודר הנאה mudar hana’ah from whom? But it sounds like
from the משנה Mishnah
that the person who is forbidden to derive benefit would not be
allowed to enter the חצר chatzer because the person who owns part
of the חצר chatzer has said this is prohibited to you and
therefore he can no longer enter. The question is, becomes, is this
about a person forbidding his own property against someone else, or is
this someone himself taking a נדר neder against someone else’s property, right?
Is it ראובן Reuven owns the left half... well not left half
and right half, let’s say ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are living
in the same חצר, chatzer, and ראובן Reuven takes a נדר, neder,
I don’t want שמעון Shimon to get any benefit from my property.
So that’s one possibility. The other possibility is ראובן Reuven says, I
take a נדר neder that I shouldn’t get any benefit from שמעון.
Shimon. Now the question that was brought up, Michael, I think you
asked the question yesterday, was about the principle אין אדם אוסר דבר
שאינו שלו, ein adam oser davar she’eino shelo, a person cannot forbid
something that doesn’t belong to him. So if that’s the case, how
can a person forbid someone from entering their own property? How can,
because of this joint ownership, if ראובן Reuven would say שמעון Shimon
you are forbidden to derive any benefit from what I own, and
that even then blocks him being able to use the entire חצר,
chatzer, which presumably he owns part of it as well, that seems
a bit sticky and that’s why some of the ראשונים Rishonim take
the other approach, that it would be that ראובן Reuven took a
נדר neder that he will not get any benefit from שמעון Shimon
and then it’s the person making himself אסור asur on someone else’s
property. But those are two different ways to read this משנה. Mishnah.
So those who say the former way, right, can say, all right,
well because of the fact that each piece is jointly owned,
therefore since it was an... and if you
say אין ברירה...
ein breira...
Well because every little bit is שלו shelo and every other bit
is not שלו shelo at the same time.
Exactly. So that's why they're compelled then to adopt the other position.
But those who think that it would be okay would either have,
I didn't go into it super in depth, it may be that
what they're saying is either they don't think that that applies here
because there is partial ownership. I think that would probably be the
best way to solve the problem for those for the other opinions.
Okay, one other point is what הנאה hana'ah are we even talking
about? The fact, you know, we said okay maybe walking through the
חצר chatzer is not really a real kind of הנאה. hana'ah. The
ר"ן Ran has a suggestion based on the גמרא Gemara in בבא
בתרא Bava Batra that because partners who have a joint ownership of
a חצר chatzer are each able to protest certain types of things,
particularly the question of permanent structures like this תנור tannur and the
רחיים, rechain, the oven and the grindstone, so it may be that
the fact that one could protest those things being put into the
חצר chatzer means that then not using that veto power, not using
that opportunity to protest is itself a certain kind of הנאה. hana'ah.
Okay,
going on to the second part of the משנה mishna where it
was only one person made the נדר, neder, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer, יכול הוא לומר לו yachol hu
lomar lo לתוך שלי אני נכנס. letoch sheli ani nichnas. He can
always say, I'm going into my part. It's basically the same principle,
but illustrated in a case where only one person took the נדר
neder and not both. ואיני נכנס לתוך שלך, ve'eini nichnas letoch shelcha,
I'm not going into your part. וכופין את הנודר למכור את חלקו,
vekofin et hanoder limkor et chelko, and the person who took the
נדר, neder, we force him to sell his portion. Now this becomes
a proof, Michael, to what you were asking before. Again, we said
two different ways to read the משנה, mishna, is it ראובן Reuven
who took a נדר neder against שמעון Shimon getting any benefit from
him, or is it ראובן Reuven who took a נדר neder for
himself not to get any benefit from שמעון? Shimon? Then it becomes
interesting to think, well then what is this adding? This is adding
the point that בית דין Beit Din can force the נודר, noder,
the person who took the נדר neder to sell his property. That
sounds at least like it was something more problematic. If you make
a נדר neder just for yourself not to get any benefit, why
should we force you to sell your property? That doesn't seem fair
at all. So that would seem like support for the other position.
So then you have a textual support and you have a conceptual
support one for either side of that debate.
So that becomes a question, how do you then see how this
fits together with the question of אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו?
ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo? Okay.
Now the third part of the משנה mishna is now no longer
the two שותפים, shutfim, the two partners taking נדרים nedarim one against
the other, but it is היה אחד מן השוק מודר באחד מהן
הנאה. haya echad min hashuk mudar be'echad mehen hana'ah. Someone else, a
third party from the שוק, shuk, from outside their חצר, chatzer, has
taken a נדר neder against deriving הנאה hana'ah from one of them.
לא יכנס לחצר. lo yikanes lachatzar. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov omer, יכול לומר לו yachol lomar lo לתוך של
חברך אני נכנס ואיני נכנס לתוך שלך. letoch shel chaverecha ani nichnas
ve'eini nichnas letoch shelcha. Either that person is then prohibited from entering
the חצר chatzer because every part of the חצר chatzer is jointly
owned and therefore it would be forbidden, or it's because רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says no, every time this person
enters into the חצר chatzer he can always say I'm going into
the other guy's property, I'm not going into your property. So again
the same illustration, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov thinks
that there's a way to navigate between the partial ownership. So we
touched on the question yesterday when you have שותפות shutfut in general,
partnership, are we talking about someone is white, someone is black, there
is a gray zone? Is it a checkerboard? Is it stripes? Is
it two halves? How do you divide those?
Every other little ד' אמות daled amot is yours and every other
one is mine.
Right, so there's a path, or alternatively, hop on stone.
Or alternatively,
this is getting into again the point about רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov is going to say יש ברירה, yesh breira,
that there is a way that once you have walked on a
certain path you can claim that that was the part that was
permitted to you.
Retroactively, in a way, as ברירה.
breira. Exactly, retroactively.
One other point about that we touched on a little bit yesterday
was the question about what about a third party having rights to
enter into a חצר? chatzer? It seems a bit strange.
And so the point about the third party,
some of the ראשונים Rishonim bring up a bit of the question
there, the ר"ן Ran quotes from the רשב"א Rashba and the ר"ה
Ra'ah
about how does that fit in with אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו
שלו? ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo? If a person is, again,
as a third party from outside this חצר chatzer and on the
one hand wants to use the חצר chatzer and on the other
hand basically didn't have any rights to begin with because it's not
his property at all. Okay, so it must be, according to some
of them it must be that he had some kind of what
he's doing in the חצר chatzer is involved. involved with one of
the residents of the חצר, chatzer, it's not just that he's going
there of his own accord, but he's gone there to do business
or to do some kind of deal with the person who lives
there, and that's part of the חברך chaverecha and the חברו. chavero.
They have some kind of a relationship before, it's not just that
he's trespassing in this חצר. chatzer. Okay.
Now
a fourth case: המודר הנאה מחברו, hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro, a person takes
a נדר. neder.
Wait, wait, but in this case we said is היה אחד מן
השוק מודר באחד מהם הנאה, hayah echad min hashuk mudar be'echad mehem
hana'ah, so
the guy in the שוק shuk said I can't get הנאה. hana'ah.
Right. Right. That's supposed to be, you know, because he had a
little bit of a debate as to how to interpret the other
one before, like I can make it אסור assur to you or
you make it אסור assur to me. Right. Right. But here we're
saying everyone is saying that the היה אחד מן השוק מודר באחד
מהם הנאה, hayah echad min hashuk mudar be'echad mehem hana'ah, the guy
from the third party foreswore any הנאה hana'ah
from one of the owners of the חצר, chatzer, right? No disagreement
there. Right. Okay, so make sure.
I'm just trying to look at this ר"ן Ran here. It's the
ר"ן Ran that's in the fifth wide line, I think: היה אחד
מן השוק מודר באחד מהם הנאה הרי זה לא יכנס לחצר. hayah
echad min hashuk mudar be'echad mehem hana'ah harei zeh lo yikanes lachatzer.
So the רשב"א Rashba says דוקא כשהוא נכנס לצורך השותפות. davka keshehu
nichnas letzorach hashutafut.
It's only when the reason he's going in is in order that
he's trying to do business with one of the partners, because otherwise
בין שצריך לשותף או שהשותף צריך לו, bein shetzarich lashutaf o shehashutaf
tzarich lo,
if he needs that person or this person needs him to come
through לפי שהחצר קנויה לכל אחד מהם. lefi shehachatzer kenuyah lechol echad
mehem. The חצר chatzer belongs
to the שותפים shutafim who own it. It doesn't belong to this
person outside, and then their business deal is what's giving him, because
otherwise what what הנאה hana'ah is there either for him to go
through? Meaning if he said he wasn't going to get הנאה hana'ah
from going through the חצר, chatzer, then there's also no there's no
benefit to him to go through the חצר chatzer as well.
Let's not get sidetracked with that, but okay.
And the ראב"ד Ra'avad disagrees with the רשב"א Rashba and says דכל
ענין שרי ולא נראו לי דבריו. dechol inyan shari velo nir'u li
devarav. So the ר"ן Ran again thinks, so the ראב"ד Ra'avad he
quotes from the ראב"ד, Ra'avad, but he says he doesn't think the
ראב"ד's Ra'avad proof works for him. Okay. So now the fourth case
in the משנה Mishnah is המודר הנאה מחברו ויש לו מרחץ ובית
הבד מושכרין בעיר. hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro veyesh lo merchatz uveit habad muskarin
ba'ir. A person takes a נדר neder not to get any הנאה
hana'ah from another person, and that person owns a bathhouse or an
olive press which are leased out in the city. אם יש לו
בהן תפיסת יד im yesh lo bahen tefisat yad אסור. assur. If
he has תפיסת יד, tefisat yad, we're going to get into in
the גמרא Gemara what this תפיסת יד tefisat yad is. It sounds
like the rental agreement, the lease agreement, is a percentage-based profit agreement
rather than a flat rate, but we'll get into that. So תפיסת
יד tefisat yad means in some way the more use that there
gets of this olive press or of this bathhouse, then the original
owner, the real owner, will benefit more, and therefore people using it,
each person who uses it, will benefit him more.
Or it's a תפיסת יד tefisat yad of the בעל בית המרחץ,
ba'al beit hamerchatz,
the owner who then leased it out to a third party.
The third party, but the person who's מודר mudar is like a
fourth person, right?
Is some other person. Is the third party, right? Let's draw the
picture. I'm sorry. That's okay. Right, so what we have is we
have the מרחץ, merchatz, this is our מרחץ. merchatz. I see.
And this is the owner, we'll call him ראובן. Reuven.
You know, you gotta have standard or in this drawing standard.
You got pools, you got water
coming out, okay good.
Okay, some some fish in there you know?
Okay okay,
so ראובן Reuven is the owner of the מרחץ merchatz and he
leased it to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so שמעון Shimon has a lease
agreement on the מרחץ. merchatz. Now the מודר mudar is over here.
Yeah, some other person.
Okay, so the מודר mudar cannot use the מרחץ merchatz because ראובן
Reuven owns it. He was מודר הנאה mudar hana'ah from ראובן. Reuven.
But that's only if ראובן Reuven has תפיסת יד tefisat yad on
שמעון's Shimon rental of the מרחץ. merchatz. So תפיסת יד tefisat yad
means that the more people use the מרחץ merchatz he makes more
money.
As opposed to a flat rate where שמעון Shimon paid ראובן Reuven
a thousand duckets for the מרחץ merchatz for six months. Right, so
that הנאה hana'ah goes over, so the מודר mudar could use the
מרחץ merchatz because only שמעון Shimon is really getting הנאה hana'ah from
שמעון.
Shimon. Right,
so we can think about different kinds of rental agreements, different kinds
of business deals, there can be percentage-based agreements, this is something like
stockholders and things like that, or more flat rate: oh, I want
to rent your מרחץ merchatz and I'm going to do with it
whatever I want, I'll make however much money I can. Well then
it's not going to be a problem for the מודר mudar to
use it because it really almost really belongs to שמעון. Shimon. שמעון.
Shimon. And that's a question of really how does rental work? If
you rent something for a long-term basis and you really retain almost
all the rights, how much more, you know, a שוכר socher has
a lot of responsibilities as a שומר. shomer. over property. Obviously, he's
been granted permission to use it almost fully, so that's really like
a temporary ownership rather than just an agreement between them. Okay. So,
if he...
I don't think it makes a difference in terms of that. I
mean, תפיסת יד Tefisat Yad means, like, you know, not necessarily the
right to the rental agreement, the income, whatever it is. תפיסת יד
Tefisat Yad means is he allowed to go in there or not,
you know?
Oh, and whether Reuven is allowed to go in, you're saying.
Yeah, whoever, whoever owns it, right? If, if, you know, I would
think it just has to do with in terms of rights of
access, not in terms of percentage of income, you know what I
mean? Reuven's allowed to just go in there, is allowed to just
kind of go in and, like, you know, do whatever it is
he needs to, then תפיסת יד, Tefisat Yad, you know, if you
will, is, is Reuven's really kind of the, quote-unquote, owner.
So you're saying that if Reuven sort of has access to the
מרחץ, merchatz, then it's as if he's still the owner and he
can go inspect it and he can go fix the drainpipe and
this and that.
Yeah, exactly, that's what I would have thought. Then he really is,
right? As opposed to, you know, you know what I mean, forget...
but then what הנאה? hana'ah?
The question then, הנאה. hana'ah. Right.
No, because then it's, quote-unquote, really Reuven's and then this מודר mudar
is, is going into Reuven's whatever it is, going into Reuven's מרחץ.
merchatz. As opposed to, if I let you, if I, if I
lent it out to you and I really can't do anything, like,
you know, in other words, if I rent my apartment to you,
I really can't go in there, you know, unless there's some sort
of agreement, whatever it is, allows me some sort of access. But
if it's yours for the year, then, and if David, you know,
makes a נדר neder not to get any הנאה hana'ah from me,
okay, then he's not, because you're really the one that owns it.
Okay, so how do I, I think I have an answer for
what you're saying, which is that if we read carefully, המודר הנאה
מחבירו ויש לו מרחץ. hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro veyeish lo merchatz.
So we could read it either way, but it seems like the
person who owns the מרחץ merchatz is the מודר הנאה. mudar hana'ah.
So I think I wrote this back-backwards, right? It's actually not like
this. If this were the case, that would be very interesting, right?
That's case, we can call this case number one, which I think
is actually wrong.
This would be if this person, the מודר, mudar, is not allowed
to get any benefit from Reuven. And, and then we're asking how
much does the תפיסת יד Tefisat Yad contribute to Reuven's ownership status
of the מרחץ, merchatz, and that's why, Michael, your question makes a
lot of sense. I think I read the משנה Mishnah wrong. I
think the מודר mudar is who we're calling Reuven. So now, if
this, if he is the מודר mudar and this is now, let's
call him Levi. So this is Shimon and Levi and the מודר.
mudar. The מודר mudar said I'm not going to get a benefit
from Levi. So that would be then saying whatever income I would
earn from him using this מרחץ merchatz will benefit me. The fact
that he goes there will benefit me. Then it depends on what
kind of rental agreement I have with Shimon. If Shimon paid me
five thousand dollars flat rate, then the fact, however many people use
the מרחץ merchatz is not going to benefit me anyway at all.
But the fact that if it was תפיסת יד, Tefisat Yad, if
I get a percentage basis, then Levi using it will benefit me
directly, I'll get five percent, and then...
that's what תפיסת יד Tefisat Yad means, תפיסת יד Tefisat Yad means
a percentage of income.
It's going to come up
in the גמרא, Gemara, so we'll see. Of course, you could argue
that the more people who use the מרחץ, merchatz, the more desirable
it is to keep renting it. In other words, in some indirect
way, but it might be that that's too indirect to actually come
under the parameters of...
right, let me just say that there's sort of a publicity value
or the marketing value that more people are using it. It's a
very interesting point.
But let's listen, yeah.
It says just how I'm reading it and the note's תוספות Tosafot
also seems to
be your first case, actually. So the notes in Artscroll said like
the first case. So then we'll have a lot more work to
do to figure... it seem-, when I read the משנה Mishnah more
carefully now, it seemed like the second case. It may be that
it's מחלוקת ראשונים machloket rishonim for all I know. So we'll have
to go back and check. Maybe I can do a little bit...
it says it in the גמרא Gemara at 46B that the ר"ן
Ran is going to explain it.
Ah, okay, so then if the ר"ן Ran goes into it even
more, let me try to prepare a little bit more about that
for tomorrow. We'll just touch on it a little bit more tomorrow
just to tie up the loose ends because it is a bit
tricky there and I don't want to get sidetracked from the rest
of the דף. daf. Okay, so that was my mistake and I'll
try to bring in a little bit more about that tomorrow. Okay,
now the next case.
And so if he has תפיסת יד, Tefisat Yad, אסור, assur, אין
לו בהן תפיסת יד, ein lo bahen Tefisat Yad, מותר. mutar. Okay,
now the next case. האומר לחבירו קונם לביתך שאני נכנס, ha'omer lachaveiro
konam leveitecha she'ani nichnas, a person says your house is קונם konam
that I shouldn't enter it, he takes a נדר neder not to
get a benefit from the house. ושדך שאני לוקח, vesadcha she'ani loke'ach,
or that your field that I won't buy it from
you, מת, met, או שמכרה לאחר, o shemecharah le'acher, if he died,
meaning the original owner, or he sold it to another person, מותר.
mutar. Then it becomes permitted to the person who took the נדר
neder because he said שדך sadcha or
ביתך. beitecha. We touched on this earlier in the גמרא Gemara where
it was discussion about exactly this question. How much do we care
about the fact that it was by-, do we say it's really
talking about בית, bayit, the house, or do we say it's really
talking about ביתך, beitecha, the fact that it is your house? And
once it changes ownership, then the נדר neder would be undone.
your house, your field. And therefore once the person either dies and
it passes to his descendants or he would sell it to a
third party, then the נדר neder would be undone. קונם בית זה
שאני נכנס, Konam bayit zeh she’ani nichnas, but this house, or שדה
זו, sadeh zo, this field שאני לוקח, she’ani loke’ach, מת או שמכרו
לאחר, met o shemechoro le’acher, אסור, assur, then it would remain prohibited
because it was the object itself that retained that status, whether or
not it was owned by the original owner.
And he'd have to go to a בית דין beit din to
nullify the vow to ever go into that field. There's no other
way because it's about the field, exactly.
Right. It would be about the field, exactly.
So,
what happens if the house falls down and then the house is
rebuilt?
That's interesting. It's not your—it is your house, but it's not that
house.
Ah, so that's a question.
If he says ביתך. beitcha. Right. If he says ביתך, beitcha, then
it's your house. So then, whatever house is presumably would still have
to be on this property. It shouldn't transfer to some other house
because then it would—it wouldn't fit with the tangible object the way
that a נדר neder has to. But if he rebuilds a new
house on the same location, perhaps ביתך beitcha would remain in effect,
but בית זה bayit zeh would not. Getting into the question of
the Ship of Theseus paradox. The what?
It's a thought experiment from Greek philosophy, which is that suppose someone
has a ship—
Right, they rebuild it like, you know, plank by plank. Well, the
ship is here, that's the ship that Theseus rode back from Crete.
And then this board rots, so they replace it. This nail rusts,
so they replace it. And after a thousand years, it's the same
ship, but none of the pieces are the original pieces. So at
what point did it stop being the first ship and did it
become the second ship? An interesting question. The רמב"ם Rambam in פרק
ח Perek Chet of הלכות נדרים Hilchot Nedarim touches on this case.
The רמב"ם Rambam says, כיצד נדר או נשבע שאינו נושא אשה פלונית
שאביה רע, Keitzad nadar o nishba she’eino nosei isha plonit she’aviha ra,
a person takes a נדר neder or a שבועה shvua to not
marry a certain woman because her father is very bad. Or he
made a תשובה. teshuva. Right, so what if a person does תשובה?
teshuva? He compares the father being bad and שאני נכנס לבית זה
שכלב רע בתוכו, she’ani nichnas labayit zeh shekelev ra betocho, I won't
go into this house because there is a bad dog in it.
So he made very clear what the reason for the נדר neder
was, and then what if those problems go away? מתו או שעשו
תשובה הרי זה מותר. Metu o she’asu teshuva harei zeh muttar. As
a dog owner, I was a bit offended that the רמב"ם Rambam
does not entertain the possibility that the dogs could do תשובה, teshuva,
but that's not for now. הרי זה מותר. Harei zeh muttar. So
the fact that the original problem was removed would then resolve the
נדר. neder. שזה כמי שנדר ונשבע ואמר שלא אשא אשה פלונית ולא
אכנס לבית זה אלא אם כן נסתלק ההיזק. Shezeh kemi shenadar venishba
ve’amar shelo essa isha plonit velo eikanes labayit zeh ela im ken
nistalek hahezek.
It was as if he made the original נדר neder conditional on
the fact, well, what if this problem will be eliminated, then it
will be okay, וכל כיוצא בזה, vechol kayotzei bazei, and anything like
this. The משנה למלך Mishneh Lamelech notes the question, well, what do
we say about this person who does תשובה? teshuva? He quotes from
the רנ"ח, Ranach, who is רבי אליהו בן חיים, Rabbi Eliyahu ben
Chaim, who was one of the big rabbis in Turkey at the
time, and he touches on the case שאם חזר לסורו שחזר האיסור
למקומו, she’im chazar lesoro shechazar ha’issur limkomo, that if a person did
תשובה teshuva and then goes back to his old ways, it's basically
like rebuilding the house. However, the
משנה למלך Mishneh Lamelech disagrees. He says, ולי אין הנידון דומה לראיה
דיש לחלק בין שהנדר נתבטל כשהנדר במקומו. Veli ein hanidon domeh laraya
deyesh lachaleik bein shehaneder nitbattel keshehaneder bimkomo. Well, he's saying, I disagree
with the רנ"ח's Ranach opinion. I think it makes much more sense
to say basically that this is a new development. Even after a
person has done תשובה teshuva and then goes back to the same
עבירה, aveira, the same sins in the past, that would be a
new case and it would not then retroactively redo the נדר neder
back into place.
Does the רמב"ם Rambam say this is an indication that the person
never really did full תשובה? teshuva?
So that would become a very interesting question, and that's something good
to get into in ראש השנה ויום כיפור Rosh Hashana veYom Kippur
time again. That's a huge question, like, how much, if you make
the same mistake a second, third time after you've done תשובה teshuva
in between, does that mean that the תשובה teshuva wasn't good or
is that just a new development? You really are a new person
and then now this is a new sin for you.
Like at the beginning of מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avodah Zarah, there's
a very interesting context there. Where—what's this—where was that reference in the
רמב"ם Rambam again?
The רמב"ם Rambam פרק ח הלכה ב Perek Chet Halacha Bet in
הלכות נדרים Hilchot Nedarim and the משנה למלך Mishneh Lamelech there.
ח' ב'? Chet Bet? פרק ח' הלכה ב'.
Perek Chet Halacha Bet. Okay, now going to the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא
להו, Iba’ya lehu, בנדרו פליגי? benadru pligi? Okay, so the case that
we are talking about, is that really בנדרו, benadru, that each of
the two partnership partners, the שותפים, shutafim, the two partners, that they
each took a נדר neder against getting benefit from the other? שנדרו
פליגי? Shenadru pligi? Is that what we're discussing, the debate between the
תנא קמא... Tanna Kamma... common with רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. הדירו זה את זה, Hediru ze et ze, right, then
מאי? mai?
So what should be the case if they הדירו זה את זה?
hediru ze et ze?
They each took a נדר neder against each other.
Not that each one took a נדר neder "I won't get benefit
from you", נדרו, nadru, but הדירו. hediru. Each one was made to
have the נדר neder by the other. ראובן Reuven says "שמעון, Shimon,
you can't get benefit from me" and שמעון Shimon says "ראובן, Reuven,
you can't get benefit from me". So that would be now, is
that a different case? So we said מאי? mai? מי אמרינן בנדרו
הוא דפליגי אבל בהדירו זה את זה מודו ליה רבנן לרבי אליעזר
בן יעקב? Mi amrinan bi-nadru hu de-pligi aval be-hediru ze et ze
modu lei Rabbanan le-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov?
So would we say that in a case of הדירו זה את
זה hediru ze et ze that the רבנן Rabbanan would agree to
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that in a case
where they each made the other person forbidden to their own property,
ראובן Reuven makes שמעון Shimon forbidden to get benefit from him and
שמעון Shimon makes ראובן Reuven forbidden to get benefit from him, then
the רבנן Rabbanan would agree to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov that assuming our ברירה bereira position that they would still
be allowed to use at least their own part of the חצר?
chatzer?
Okay. ומאי? V-mai? So why?
Because...
let me just find the next bit here.
One second. דכי אנוסים דמו, De-chi anusim damu, right, because exactly that,
that they are אנוסים, anusim, meaning that what? Each person, it's not
that I made a choice to make someone else's property forbidden to
me, he made me forbidden. What, you're going to tell me I
can't go into my apartment house? I can't get into my house?
How am I supposed to... you're denying me access. So that's kind
of getting into the אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו.
Ein
adam oser davar she-eino shelo.
If each of them owns 50% ownership of this property and then
שמעון Shimon in a spiteful mood says "Hey ראובן, Reuven, you can't
get any benefit from what's mine", so he's אנוס, anus, he's totally
powerless in this situation. Even though both of them have made the
same decision. So they really don't like each other. They really made
this very spiteful decision to block each other's access, but we have
to allow them at least some access because otherwise it would be
impossible for them to use the חצר chatzer at all, which is
what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was saying.
So a third party should go in and buy it for a
song?
Well, that's an interesting solution to the problem, but it's not suggested
here. Okay. או דילמא, O dilma, or alternatively we have a different
way to read the משנה. Mishna. או דילמא אפילו בהדירו זה את
זה פליגי רבנן. O dilma afilu be-hediru ze et ze pligi Rabbanan.
Or should we say that the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma position that
they cannot use, זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו, ze
nichnas le-toch shelo ve-ze nichnas le-toch shelo, even in the case of
הדירו זה את זה hediru ze et ze and that אונס ones
should not help. Okay. So איבעיא להו, Ibaya lehu, that's our question.
Yeah, now that I say this, I mean you really could have
suggested alright, they're stuck, they have to sell it to a third
person. They're like, they can't get out of it, you know what
I mean?
Well, in the case of a one-directional נדר, neder, we do say
the בית דין Beis Din forces them to sell it. It becomes
a question how come that wasn't suggested in the bidirectional case and
if it would work. It may be just that because of the
fact that we almost want them to get out of it, right?
If we want to force them to get out of it, maybe
making them live with it will accelerate the process because they'll see
how frustrating it is to live this way, perhaps. Okay. תא שמע,
Ta shma, so now we're going to try to bring a support
for one of the opinions in the question. תא שמע היה אחד
מהם מודר הנאה מחבירו...
Ta shma haya echad mehem
mudar hana'ah me-chavero... היה אחד מהם מודר הנאה מחבירו. Haya echad mehem
mudar hana'ah me-chavero.
So the second case in the משנה Mishna should be support for
which half? It should be support for the fact that אונס ones
is not enough because פליגי רבנן, pligi Rabbanan,
because the רבנן Rabbanan there still disagree with רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and do not admit, agree to his position,
and therefore it sounds like the fact that they are אנוסים, anusim,
it was היה אחד מהם מודר הנאה מחבירו, haya echad mehem mudar
hana'ah me-chavero, that he
took... not he's נודר הנאה מחבירו, noder hana'ah me-chavero, he was מודר
הנאה מחבירו, mudar hana'ah me-chavero, that was a case of אונס ones
and nonetheless the רבנן Rabbanan still disagree with רבי אליעזר בן יעקב.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
Well, that was sort of that other question we had until you
read that, like that, what?
Exactly. Okay. או, O, so the גמרא Gemara just says "Okay, תני
נדור", tani nadur so teach it, don't say think of it as
מודר הנאה, mudar hana'ah, when even when it says מודר הנאה, mudar
hana'ah, it could really mean נדור מחבירו, nadur me-chavero, that he took
a נדר neder to not get benefit from his friend. נדור מחבירו
מחבירו הנאה. Nadur me-chavero me-chavero hana'ah. הכי נמי מסתברא דתני סיפא וכופין
את הנודר למכור חלקו.
Hachi nami mistabra de-tani seifa ve-kofin es
ha-noder limkor chelko. Ah, but
so then why should it make sense that the second case where
it's only one-directional נדר, neder, why should we then force him to
sell his property if it wasn't a case of אונס? ones? Meaning
what do we have? We have on the one hand, if it
was מודר הנאה, mudar hana'ah, if he was taken the נדר neder
against, if ראובן Reuven said "שמעון, Shimon, you cannot get benefit from
me", so that's אונס, ones, that's against his will, it's totally forced.
So then maybe that would give us room to say maybe the
רבנן Rabbanan should agree with רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov. However, the גמרא Gemara suggests תני נדור מחבירו, tani nadur me-chavero,
think of it not as מודר הנאה mudar hana'ah but as נדור
הנאה, nadur hana'ah, but then why would it make sense to say
כופין... kofin... כופין את הנודר למכור את חלקו kofin es hanoder limkor
es chelko that he should be forced to sell his property? Cause
he's the נדור, nadur, he's the one who was taken the נדר
neder against.
So how should he then sorry, he's not, he's the other way.
But כופין את הנודר, kofin es hanoder, the person who took the
נדר neder would be forced to sell his property. So therefore it
must be a case of אונס. ones. It must be that Reuven
said, Shimon, you cannot get any benefit from mine. And almost as
a punishment, that's the only way it makes sense to say that
Reuven would have to sell his property. If Reuven said, I choose
not to get any benefit from Shimon, so then okay fine, he's
allowed to do that. Why should we make him sell his property?
That wouldn't make any sense.
Okay. אי אמרת בשלמא דנדר הוא דהיינו דקתני כופין. i amart bishlama
d'neder hu d'hainu d'katani kofin. So if you will say that דנדר
הוא d'nadar hu that he took the נדר, neder, that's why it
says כופין. kofin. אלא אי אמרת דאדריה ela i amart d'adrei that
he made him have the נדר, neder, meaning that Reuven said Shimon
you cannot get benefit from me, אמאי כופין אותו? amai kofin oso?
הא מנאנס אניס. ha menanas anis. Because
why should he be forced to sell his property? Because מנאנס אניס
menanas anis that he's he's that's the question, right?
אמאי כופין אותו, amai kofin oso, right.
אמאי כופין אותו, amai kofin oso, why should we force him to?
הא מנאנס אניס ha menanas anis because the fact is no, even
in that case he is forced, so even if you'll say that
he's forced, that's why we have to say that he should be
forced to sell his property
because it was against against his power of it. Okay.
No so that's part of the no so that's
part of the question.
Right right right that's part of the exactly. כופין אותו kofin oso
הא מנאנס אניס ha menanas anis right because the fact that he
was forced to do it so how why should he try to
give up his property? Right, why should he be forced to give
up his property? So what's the answer? אמר רבה. amar Rava. So
Rava responds, אמר זעירי מחלוקת שיש בה כדי חלוקה. amar Zeiri machlokes
sheyesh bah k'dei chalukah. Ah,
so what are we talking about? We have two different kinds of
חצר. chatzer. We have יש בה כדי חלוקה. yesh bah k'dei chalukah.
יש בה כדי חלוקה yesh bah k'dei chalukah that it's big enough
that it could be subdivided such that each of them has a
reasonable amount of space and then there's some communal area in between.
However, שיש בה כדי חלוקה. sheyesh bah k'dei chalukah. אבל אין בה
כדי חלוקה aval ein bah k'dei chalukah if it is so small
that it could not give each of them a private area in
the חצר chatzer and then the communal space would still be in
dispute, דברי הכל מותר divrei hakol mutar because then according to everyone
it would be permitted, meaning that the rabbis would agree with רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that we must employ זה
נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו. zeh nichnas l'soch shelo v'zeh
nichnas l'soch shelo. Presumably therefore that it might be that the רבנן
rabbanan agree with רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov about
I mean we're going to now we have a חצר chatzer which
is יש בה כדי חלוקה. yesh bah k'dei chalukah.
A large a large חצר.
chatzer. Okay? And this person lives here and this person lives here.
It may be that the רבנן rabbanan disagree with רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov only about the parts of the field
over here or or something because each of them really does get
his own חלוקה chalukah even conceptually even though they own the entire
חצר chatzer jointly. The רבנן rabbanan would perhaps agree
or sorry the רבנן rabbanan only disagree with רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov about the part that's under under contest, about
the public use space. But in a small case in a small
חצר chatzer where they're each here and if we were to try
to give them each a private space they would be overlapping and
interfering with each other so therefore here the רבנן rabbanan must agree
to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that we have
to say זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו zeh nichnas
l'soch shelo v'zeh nichnas l'soch shelo kind of ברירה. breira.
No matter where
no matter where he walks because the entire space really would have
been enough for one person's private חצר chatzer and the fact that
there are two people there means that it's so small they couldn't
really divide it effectively and therefore that it would have to say
דברי הכל מותר. divrei hakol mutar. So אמר ליה רב יוסף. amar
leh Rav Yosef. Rav Yosef disagrees with Rava. הרי בית הכנסת דכמי
שאין בו כדי חלוקה דמי.
harei beis haknesses d'chimi
she'ein bo k'dei chalukah dami. What about a בית הכנסת? beis haknesses?
בית הכנסת beis haknesses we can think of as a public use
space. We touched a little bit on a question of corporations yesterday.
So a בית הכנסת beis haknesses in some sense is a corporate
entity owned by the residents of the city in some sense. The
בית הכנסת beis haknesses of a large city is in some sense
owned by all of כל ישראל. kol Yisrael.
The גמרא Gemara in מגילה Megillah discussing about what you can sell
for what use and can can the residents of the city sell
the בית הכנסת beis haknesses to buy a ספר תורה sefer torah
for example or to buy מטפחות mitpachos for their ספרים. sefarim. So
for a large city you're not allowed to sell the בית הכנסת
beis haknesses because it was built on the intent of not just
the residents of the city but for any passers-by, anyone who'd come
on a business trip. However, a small city, a small town, their
בית הכנסת beis haknesses was only built for their use, so that
sort of is a sense of corporate ownership or is it more
broadly, who are the shareholders? So that's a question. So בית הכנסת
דכמי שאין בו כדי חלוקה דמי. beis haknesses d'chimi she'ein bo k'dei
chalukah dami. A בית הכנסת beis haknesses is similar to a case
of a חצר chatzer which is so small that it cannot be
divided because even if the בית הכנסת beis haknesses is very large.
the function of the בית הכנסת Beit HaKnesset is that it cannot
be broken up. This person has this part and this person has
this part. And the next משניות mishnayot are going to deal with
the case of בית הכנסת, Beit HaKnesset, what if one person tries
to take נדר neder against the other? And what about their use
of the בית הכנסת? Beit HaKnesset? דכי שאין בו כדי חלוקה דמי
ותנן שניהם אסורים בדבר של אותה העיר. De-chi she-ein bo kidei chalukah
dami ve-tenan sheneihem assurim bidvar shel otah ha-ir. And the משנה mishnah
is going to go on to say שניהם אסורים, sheneihem assurim, both
of them are forbidden with something בדבר של אותה העיר bidvar shel
otah ha-ir of that city.
Meaning if I took a נדר neder against you, you can't, I
say you're, you can't use the שול? shul?
Right, so because we are each as if shareholders in the ownership
of the שול, shul, then the fact that you took a נדר
הנאה neder hana'ah against me would mean that you would, I would
not be allowed to use the שול shul or you would not
be allowed to use the שול shul depending on the terms of
the נדר. neder. Okay, so then the next משניות mishnayot are going
to deal with that. Okay, so but של אותה העיר. shel otah
ha-ir. אלא אמר רב יוסף, Ella, amar Rav Yosef, so it must
be therefore, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, I have a parallel
case, the case of בית הכנסת Beit HaKnesset is parallel to even
the small חצר. chatzer. So רבא, Rava, you say that in a
small חצר, chatzer, רבנן זה נכנס
לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך
שלו,
Rabbanan, zeh nichnas letokh shelo vezeh nichnas
letokh shelo, right?
זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו Zeh nichnas letokh shelo
vezeh nichnas letokh shelo because רבא Rava says רבנן Rabbanan must agree
with רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov for a small
חצר chatzer because the only place that should be under dispute between
them is the public use space, but since their private use space
would be so small, it would overlap and therefore there would be
no other way of resolving the situation. So רבא Rava would say
that it would apply and that רבנן Rabbanan would agree with רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef
says I don't know what you're talking about, a בית הכנסת Beit
HaKnesset is parallel to the case of a small חצר chatzer and
the משנה mishnah says that even in the case of בית הכנסת
Beit HaKnesset it would remain אסור. assur.
Right, but it's not the same because בית כנסת Beit Knesset is
all public space as opposed to being all private space.
Okay, so that's an interesting point. So we'll have to get into
especially more when we get into the בית הכנסת Beit HaKnesset stuff
as
well. Okay, אלא אמר רב יוסף אמר דרימא מחלוקת שאין בה כדי
חלוקה אבל יש בה כדי חלוקה דברי הכל אסור.
Ella amar Rav Yosef amar de-rema machloket she-ein bah kidei chalukah aval
yesh bah kidei
chalukah divrei hakol assur.
So רב יוסף Rav Yosef says in a small חצר chatzer that
is so small that it cannot be subdivided, that's where the משנה
mishnah has a מחלוקת machloket between the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. And רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov can say זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך
שלו zeh nichnas letokh shelo vezeh nichnas letokh shelo and רבנן Rabbanan
say אסור, assur, it's so small. And in the case of a
large חצר, chatzer, everyone agrees, even רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov agrees with the רבנן Rabbanan that you cannot say זה
נכנס לתוך שלו, zeh nichnas letokh shelo, rather that the entire חצר
chatzer would be forbidden because in a large חצר chatzer where there
is, it would be possible for each of them to have their
own area and therefore it wouldn't, you wouldn't have a reasonable ability
to say that wherever you're going is זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה
נכנס לתוך שלו, zeh nichnas letokh shelo vezeh nichnas letokh shelo, so
because it's so large, then even רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov would say אסור. assur.
Like, wouldn't we understand that like, you know, I'm allowed to go
out to like, does everyone, the, you know, like I get the
ד' אמות daled amot in front of my door, I mean everybody,
like that, you know, I would think so.
Well we're going to get into that further on as well I
think. Yes.
Is this large courtyard also jointly owned?
Yeah,
in all of these cases we're talking about the two partners who
have joint ownership over the חצר. chatzer.
That was the model that we had there about the idea of
the lines or the lines, you know, where you can't, gray.
Right, so it is probably it's something like a gray area. The
question becomes can רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov say
retroactively that we put it into black and white? That, that each
person has the ברירה, bereirah, has the ability to retroactively designate this
part that I'm using now is the part that I was allowed
to use and another part will be the part that's for you
and the sort of, and again, the fact that there was this
joint ownership agreement from the beginning and then you're trying to clarify
now what are the terms of that initial agreement is a different
kind of ברירה bereirah than other cases of ברירה bereirah where there
was no initial status to begin with. And when you're separating תרומה
terumah and you take the תרומה terumah out of the wine barrel,
that bit at the bottom is, was never there to begin with.
Here there was at least the purchase agreement of the חצר chatzer
beforehand and now you're trying to clarify the details of it.
But if it's the large courtyard and it's divided and it's jointly
owned, then,
when do, how do we define for example what we're doing here
whether one party is receiving...
But it was never divided in this case of a large courtyard.
That was the whole problem. It was never divided. If it was
actually divided, you wouldn't have a question.
Right, the large courtyard is large enough to be divided but it
is not currently divided.
So then this question of receiving benefit... Right, is, in other words
if we say you use this area and I'm going to use
that area, you're saying that hadn't happened yet?
They have not yet made such an agreement. They are currently both
operating on the assumption that the entire courtyard is fair use for
either of them to use jointly as is reasonable. They can even,
I, you know, if I live on this חצר chatzer I'm allowed
to put up a תנור, tannur, an oven, for my own personal
use because that's part of what you... to use of that, therefore,
even if it's a public use חצר, chatzer, I can still put
my oven there or I can raise my chickens there. Now we've
made this נדר, neder, okay, so now all of that benefit that
we were that was the operating principle of our use of a
חצר, chatzer, the personal benefit that I'm getting now from property which
is technically someone else's, now has become problematic. So the question is
under what part of the חצר chatzer did that apply? Does that
apply to the part right outside my door?
Sounds like according to this is a debate between רבה Rabba and
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. רבה Rabba thinks that even the Rabbis agree
to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov for a small
חצר chatzer because it's so small, there each of their even private
use space in the חצר chatzer would overlap. And רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says, no, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov would
agree with the Rabbis in a case of a large חצר chatzer
and they really are debating about the public use space of the
חצר chatzer that they both have rights to.
I was also thinking it is understood that you know it's a
big חצר, chatzer, that the part right in front of your door
is obviously yours, that you can go in there.
So I think that does come up in the גמרא Gemara later,
I don't remember exactly, but I think it does come up later,
is exactly that point, which is that even in something which technically
the entire thing is owned by all of the שותפין, shutafin, that
at least sort of implicit in that agreement was the fact that
like yeah but the part right by my door is more of
my property.
You shouldn't put your plants there, you know, and like have your
doghouse there, I think it'd be I'd be very upset to say
get it out of here, move it in front of yours.
Right. And that again some of these things get into question, practical
questions about living with neighbors and how you know who mows this
part of the lawn or who you know if you put your
wet boots in the hallway of your apartment building and it drips
water everywhere even if it's in right in front of your door
maybe that isn't an appropriate use of the hallway because it's a
common area. So those are a lot of questions about how does
this apply
to really apartment living particularly because you have that kind of public
common space in between the different apartments or townhouses something like that
and have a shared parking lot. What do you do in the
parking lot? What can you not
do? Okay. אבל יש בה כדי חלוקה דברי הכל אסור. Aval yesh
bah kedei chaluka divrei hakol assur. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef disagrees
with רבה Rabba and says no if it is large enough that
is a case where even רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov would agree with the Rabbis that the whole thing would be
אסור. assur. אמר רב הונא הלכה כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Amar Rav
Huna halacha keRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. So רב הונא Rav Huna comes
along and says fine we should follow רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov.
We don't know
which
version though. Ah, but the point is that רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says we can at least employ the principle
of זה נכנס לתוך שלו וזה נכנס לתוך שלו. ze nichnas letoch
shelo veze nichnas letoch shelo. וכן אמר רבי אלעזר הלכה כרבי אליעזר
בן יעקב. Vechein amar Rabbi Elazar halacha keRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. And
even one of the תנאים, Tannaim, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, said that
the הלכה halacha should follow רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov. So we have life. Fine. So at least we have the
operating principle that if רבי אליעזר בן יעקב's Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
position is based on the idea of יש ברירה, yesh brira, this
is now become one of the sources to say under certain circumstances
we can say יש ברירה. yesh brira. And then the question becomes
okay so how does ברירה brira work again just to refresh?
So the ברירה brira point is that saying זה נכנס לתוך שלו
וזה נכנס לתוך שלו ze nichnas letoch shelo veze nichnas letoch shelo
is saying that whenever you walk through the חצר chatzer that you're
saying the part I'm walking in right now was the part that
was designated for me to be in.
So the ברירה brira is the grammar so to speak of that
position that wherever I'm walking it's the other guy.
Exactly. No, wherever I'm walking is mine, rather is mine.
And the contrary, now wait, now
so why
even though the original purchase agreement for the jointly owned חצר chatzer
was that the entire space would be jointly owned, I can later
come along and walk through and say right now this is mine.
But
not in a big חצר chatzer according to the second version.
So wait, but here's my question: why does asserting or why does
framing the situation as a situation of אונס onus better justify that
argument? Because it was against my will in the first place that
it was proscribed that I couldn't walk there. So we had an
agreement that was against my will that I should stop my car
where there's a stop sign. In other words, there's a lot of
things against my will but the law still. Okay.
So what did we have? We had a joint agreement between the
two of us to buy this חצר, chatzer, which the operating assumption
was that each of us would have fifty percent rights to the
חצר. chatzer. And now comes ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven says, שמעון,
Shimon, you are forbidden to get benefit from my fifty percent of
the share. There the אונס onus situation is really
foundational because the original the reality of the entire arrangement is based
on a שותפות shutafut which is now against my will being undermined
so
to speak.
And again, what is that שותפות? shutafut? Is that saying I get
fifty percent use a hundred percent of the time? Is that saying
I get a hundred percent use fifty percent of the time? You
know, we switch off Sunday, Tuesday, Thursday and Monday, Wednesday, Friday? Those
are different questions that come up across ש"ס. Shas. between two people
own an animal together, two people own a slave together, two people
own different tools, who gets to use it when, those are the
questions that come up regarding what are the principles, what is assumed
agreement about fifty percent ownership, what does that mean? So that gets
into a lot of questions.
Yes, but then again, it's according to the second version, it was
a big שדה, Sadeh, then it doesn't work, and I can't say
I'm going through. Wait, but רבנו יעקב Rabbeinu Yaakov agrees to רבנן
Rabbanan that it's אסור. assur. He would agree that it's because the
אונס oness
question, even if it was a case of אונס, oness, it wouldn't
be such אונס oness because still, it's a big one. Meaning, presumably
assuming that the part
right by your door, you would still get.
But I'll have to go back and check some of that for
tomorrow.
Okay, getting in and out of, fine.
Right, so that's part of the question. The only way to get
out, I guess maybe if I have a house, then right.
Okay. Yeah, something like that. Although they also have the door the
other side, but if there isn't, how do I get through, you
know what I mean? This suggests something we discussed usually that when
you make an arrangement, you should go through all the details as
best as you can. Yeah, for sure. You can get stuck with
a, when you make a contract, if there's one clause that's left
hanging, you say, ah, it's fine. Somebody can exploit that, right?
One other point, this is reminding me of, I think, a reasonably
well-known גמרא Gemara about, or I think it's a גמרא, Gemara, about
people who are riding in a boat, right? And one person says,
I'm drilling a hole underneath my seat, and someone else says, well,
is this really גמרא? Gemara? Maybe it's just a story, I don't
remember now. I'll have to go check that too. For some reason,
I thought it was from the גמרא. Gemara. That a person is
drilling the hole under his seat and somebody says, oh what are
you doing? You're going to drown us all. He says, ah, I'm
just drilling under my seat. So that becomes a question, even under
partnership agreements, social contract kind of things. The stop sign example is
a good example that you agree to certain conditions of jointly owned
property or jointly used property. You can't just say, well, I own
this seat in the airplane so I'm going to, you know, whatever.
Okay. So that's again part of this discussion. Again, the אונס oness
question, if a person took a נדר, neder, the person took a
נדר neder to make the field אסור, assur, that you're kind of
stuck. Okay. The last little bit here is about תפיסת יד. tfisat
yad. וכמה תפיסת יד, Vekamah tfisat yad, how much is this תפיסת
יד? tfisat yad? That's why we were saying תפיסת יד tfisat yad
is a percentage. So how much percentage
is enough to make it problematic? Because even if you have a
one percent תפיסת יד, tfisat yad,
it's probably not enough הנאה hana'ah to really make it such a
difference that you care whether one person is going to use the
מרחץ. merchatz. You care if ten people use the מרחץ, merchatz, you
care if a hundred people use the מרחץ, merchatz, but if one
person uses the מרחץ, merchatz, it's not going to be a big
deal. וכמה תפיסת יד? Kamah tfisat yad? אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, or alternatively, maybe it's not just about the money, but it
is also about how much, like we were saying, sort of residual
ownership, even in the case of this lease, that the original owner
is still hovering around. So how much a percentage of the proceeds
is he getting? Does that determine how invested he still is in
the day-to-day
success of this מרחץ? merchatz? וכמה תפיסת יד? Kamah tfisat yad? אמר
רב נחמן למחצה לשליש ולרביע. Amar Rav Nachman: Lemechtza, leshlish, uleravia. Okay?
Whether it's half, whether it's a third, whether it's a quarter. אבל
בבציר לא. Aval babatzir lo. בציר Batzir means picking. Right, so it
means picking, also means less. So, בציר, batzir, if it were less
than that, meaning if it were either less than a quarter, less
than twenty-five percent, okay. אביי אמר אפילו בבציר אסור. Abaye amar: Afilu
babatzir assur. היכי דמי דשרו דמקבל בטסקא. Heichi dami? Dishru d'mikabel b'taska.
So that is, אביי Abaye is saying even if it's less, why?
Because...
I'm sorry, one sec.
I totally forgot. What's the word טסקא? taska? I'm very sorry. Someone
has the English to tell me the word טסקא? taska? I'm very
embarrassed.
Yeah, I forget what it means here. יהיב ליה אהוכר... yahiv lei
ahoker... the רש״י Rashi says it. יהיב ליה אהוכר דטפי מההוא מסא.
Yahiv lei ahoker detfei mehahu masa. טסקא... Taska... Oh right, it's exactly
what we were saying.
Oh,
this is the exact point. Oh, this is about the point about
fixed rate and percentage, right? Okay.
מסא בכל שנה ושנה טסקא. Masa bechol shanah veshanah taska. Oh, a
tax. Right. It's a fixed annual... Right, it's a fixed fee.
Right. Okay. רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying למחצה לשליש ולרביע. lemechtza,
leshlish, uleravia. It's a percentage. I'm sorry, so this is where I
got it from... got all mixed up when you translate into English.
Okay.
אמר רב נחמן למחצה לשליש ולרביע. Amar Rav Nachman: Lemechtza, leshlish, uleravia.
If it's a percentage basis of half, a third, a quarter, אבל
בבציר לא, aval babatzir lo, but presumably less shouldn't apply, okay. אבל
אביי אמר אפילו בבציר אסור. Aval Abaye amar: Afilu babatzir assur. If
it's a percentage, but even less than twenty-five percent is still problem
because it's a percentage, because each person coming in is going to
benefit you more, the more business you get, you earn more, and
therefore you'll still be getting הנאה hana'ah from the fact that one
more person used the bathhouse. היכי דמי דשרו? Heichi dami dishru? So
what... and the case...
That's אביי. Abaye.
That
is אביי. Abaye. It must be
המקבל בטסקא. hamikabel betaska. If you're not earning any
money, you don't have to
have the תפיסת יד tfisat yad of earning
money. Exactly.
Sorry, exactly, so there is that point.
Meaning the assumption was, right,
what would be exactly, if you had only by fixed rate, then
that's a way to lease out your property with no
תפיסת יד.
tfisat yad. So תפיסת יד tfisat yad is an ongoing investment in
the success of this business venture. Therefore, it must be by percentage.
It means that I'm still, I care how many people come to
the bathhouse. So if one more person will come to the bathhouse,
I'll get more benefit. And therefore,
the percentage basis אביי Abaye is saying, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, I
understand רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, you're saying only 25 percent but not
10 percent? 10 percent you'll still get 10 percent proceeds of each
and every person who comes in. So I'm not exactly sure what
רב נחמן Rav Nachman would say back to אביי, Abaye, it sounds
like אביי Abaye has defeated רב נחמן Rav Nachman with his logic.
We have to think about רב נחמן Rav Nachman's position, why only
down to a quarter but not less.
But what about this other question that we had? Who, you know,
is it like the מודר? mudar?
Right, so then this is why I was saying that it was
by my second case, but you were saying earlier the footnote here,
so it must be that this long רן Ran is talking about,
right, this long רן Ran starting with
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אפילו בביצי מאסור, afillu bebatzimasur, not בבציר. bebatzir.
That's talking, ah, it's talking about the chickens.
Yeah, so this phrase מכדי תילתא
שליש ורביע...
machtela shilash
verivea... sorry,
yeah,
this phrase is a standard phrase. I remember learning like
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma also like with גניבה. geneiva. Right. But
my understanding from there is that מכדי תילתא שליש
ורביע machtela shilash verivea means what is common practice in the marketplace
in this locality for this type of a thing. So that's why
you don't have to go lower than a... like you don't have
to keep on going lower. Right. These seem to be like the
standard. It's לאו דוקא. lav davka. Right. Whatever the standard is set
in the market for this type of transaction, that would define תפיסת
יד tfisat yad by that
definition.
Right. Great. Okay, so this is the end of מ״ז עמוד ב׳
Mem Zayin Amud Bet and we will continue tomorrow...
no, the end of מ״ו עמוד ב׳.
Mem Vav Amud Bet. Tomorrow we'll start with מ״ז עמוד א׳ Mem
Zayin Amud Alef right at the top.
This is the same case with the sharecropper, same thing, you know,
a sharecropper...